# Xing Liu

https://orcid.org/0000-0002-4637-0109

https://scholar.google.com/citations?user=Zbw gAwAAAAJ

https://github.com/hint1412

xing.liu@me.gatech.edu X.Liu1993@hotmail.com +1 (401) 489 3049

#### RESEARCH INTERESTS

My Mission is to design *more mechanically resilient* engineering materials and structures (with exceptional strength and fracture/fatigue resistance) for aerospace and energy applications while enabling *more socioresilient* utilization of these materials throughout their *entire* life cycle. The success of the mission hinges on the integration of *multiscale modeling* (*e.g.*, atomistic modeling, crystal plasticity modeling, phase field modeling), *advanced machine learning* (*e.g.*, generative AI), and *multiscale materials characterization*.

Scientific Endeavors that underpin my mission include i) advancing theories of strength for materials exhibiting exceptional structural, microstructural, and/or compositional heterogeneity, e.g., complex concentrated alloys, additively manufactured materials, ceramic composites, ii) developing experimentally validated models with uncertainty quantification to predict the inelastic deformation and fracture of materials under normal and extreme conditions, iii) devising multiphysics methodologies for manipulating material microstructures and for rejuvenating, repairing, and recycling damaged heterogeneous materials.

Concurrently with the research thrust described above, I am committed to constructing a machine learning-enabled open-access platform for materials characterization.

# **SCIENTIFIC SKILLS**

- **Programming**: Python, Fortran, Matlab, TensorFlow, Scikit-learn, LaTeX
- Computational: ABAQUS, ANSYS, FEAP, FEniCS, LAMMPS, VASP, Creo Parametric, HyperMesh
- **Experimental:** Instron Testing Machine, Nano-indentation, Digital Image Correlation

# **EMPLOYMENT HISTORY**

# Georgia Institute of Technology, USA

Postdoctoral Fellow, George W. Woodruff School of Mechanical Engineering

August 2022 – Present

Working with Prof. Ting Zhu

# **Brown University, USA**

Postdoctoral Research Associate, School of Engineering

February 2022 – July 2022

Working with Profs. Brian W. Sheldon, Nitin P. Padture, Huajian Gao

# **Brown University, USA**

Graduate Research Assistant, Solid Mechanics, School of Engineering

2014 - December 2021

Working with Prof. Huajian Gao

#### **EDUCATION**

#### Ph.D. Brown University, USA

2014 - December 2021

Research Assistant, Solid Mechanics, School of Engineering

Dissertation: Integrated simulation, machine learning and experimental approaches in small-scale mechanical characterization of materials

Dissertation Committee: Prof. Huajian Gao (advisor), Prof. Brian W. Sheldon, Prof. Nitin P. Padture

Tsien Hsue-Shen Elite Class in Mechanics, Department of Engineering Mechanics

# **AWARDS & HONORS**

Outstanding Reviewer Award, Acta/Scripta Materialia

2022

#### TEACHING EXPERIENCE

• Guest Lecturer, Statics (Instructor: Prof. Ting Zhu)

Spring 2023

• Teaching Assistant, Advanced Engineering Mechanics (Instructor: Prof. Huajian Gao)

Spring 2017

# PEER REVIEWED JOURNAL PUBLICATIONS († AUTHORS WITH EQUAL CONTRIBUTIONS)

- [1] X. Liu, C.E. Athanasiou, C. López-Pernía, T. Zhu, N.P. Padture, B.W. Sheldon, H. Gao, "Tailoring the toughening effects in two-dimensional nanomaterial-reinforced ceramic matrix composites", *Journal of Applied Mechanics* (Accepted).
- [2] Z. Dai, M.C. Doyle, X. Liu, M. Hu, Q. Wang, C.E. Athanasiou, Y. Liu, B.W. Sheldon, H. Gao, S.F. Liu, N.P. Padture, "The mechanical behavior of metal-halide perovskites: Elasticity, plasticity, fracture, and creep", *Scripta Materialia* (2023).
- [3] C.E. Athanasiou<sup>†</sup>, <u>X. Liu</u><sup>†</sup>, B. Zhang<sup>†</sup>, T. Cai, C. Ramirez, N.P. Padture, J. Lou, B.W. Sheldon, H. Gao, "Integrated simulation, machine learning, and experimental approach to characterizing fracture instability in indentation pillar-splitting of materials", *Journal of the Mechanics and Physics of Solids* (2022).
- [4] C.E. Athanasiou<sup>†</sup>, X. Liu<sup>†</sup>, M.Y. Jin, E. Nimon, S. Visco, C. Lee, M. Park, J. Yun, N.P. Padture, H. Gao, B.W. Sheldon, "Rate-dependent deformation of amorphous sulfide glass electrolytes for solid-state batteries", *Cell Reports Physical Science* (2022).
- [5] Z. Dai, S. Li, X. Liu, M. Chen, C.E. Athanasiou, B.W. Sheldon, H. Gao, P. Guo, N.P. Padture, "Dual-interface reinforced flexible perovskite solar cells for enhanced performance and mechanical reliability", *Advanced Materials* (2022).
- [6] X. Liu<sup>†</sup>, C.E. Athanasiou<sup>†</sup>, N.P. Padture, B.W. Sheldon, H. Gao, "Knowledge extraction and transfer in data-driven fracture mechanics", *Proceedings of the National Academy of Sciences* (2021).
- [7] B. Zhang<sup>†</sup>, X. Liu<sup>†</sup>, H. Guo<sup>†</sup>, K. Yang, G. Gao, B.W. Sheldon, H. Gao, J. Lou, "Quantitative in-situ study of strength-governed interfacial failure between h-BN and polymer-derived ceramic", *Acta Materialia* (2021).
- [8] X. Liu, C.E. Athanasiou, N.P. Padture, B.W. Sheldon, H. Gao, "A machine learning approach to fracture mechanics problems", *Acta Materialia* (2020).
- [9] A.K. Dickerson, X. Liu, T. Zhu, D.L. Hu, "Fog spontaneously folds mosquito wings", *Physics of Fluids* (2015).

# INVITED/CONTRIBUTED CONFERENCE TALKS

- [1] X. Liu, "<u>Keynote</u> Talk Integrated Simulation, Machine learning, and Experimental Approaches in Small-Scale Mechanical Characterization of Materials", *The Society of Engineering Science (SES) Annual Technical Meeting*, October 2022.
- [2] **X. Liu**, C.E. Athanasiou, T. Zhu, N.P. Padture, B.W. Sheldon, H. Gao, "Contributed Talk Tailoring toughening effects in two-dimensional nanomaterial-reinforced ceramic matrix composites", *The Society of Engineering Science (SES) Annual Technical Meeting*, October 2023.

- [3] **X. Liu**, T. Zhu, "Contributed Talk Investigating precipitate hardening through discrete dislocation analysis", *The Society of Engineering Science (SES) Annual Technical Meeting*, October 2023.
- [4] **X. Liu**, C.E. Athanasiou, "Contributed Talk Integrating Simulation, Machine Learning, and Experimental Approaches for High-Throughput Small-Scale Fracture Investigations", *15<sup>th</sup> International Conference on Fracture (ICF15)*, June 2023.
- [5] **X. Liu**, C.E. Athanasiou, N.P. Padture, B.W. Sheldon, H. Gao, "Contributed Talk Knowledge extraction and transfer in data-driven fracture mechanics", *ASCE Engineering Mechanics Institute (EMI) Conference*, June 2023.
- [6] **X. Liu**, C.E. Athanasiou, N.P. Padture, B.W. Sheldon, H. Gao, "Contributed Talk Integrating Simulation, Machine Learning, and Experimental Approaches in Small-Scale Mechanical Characterization of Materials", *The Minerals, Metals & Materials Society (TMS) 2023 Annual Meeting & Exhibition*, March 2023.
- [7] **X. Liu**, C.E. Athanasiou, B. Zhang, N.P. Padture, J. Lou, B.W. Sheldon, H. Gao, "Contributed Talk Integrated cohesive zone and J-integral approaches to characterizing indentation-induced pillar fracture instability", 19<sup>th</sup> U.S. National Congress on Theoretical and Applied Mechanics (USNC/TAM), June 2022.
- [8] **X. Liu**, C.E. Athanasiou, N.P. Padture, B.W. Sheldon, H. Gao, "Contributed Talk A machine learning approach to fracture mechanics problems", 2020 Virtual Materials Research Society (MRS) Fall Meeting & Exhibit, November 2020.

#### ADVISING & MENTORING EXPERIENCE

Zhiming Dai & Cheng Wan, Master students, Georgia Tech

Fall 2023

Co-advising with Prof. Christos E. Athanasiou (Georgia Tech) on renovating and advertising our Machine Learning-Enabled Open-Access Platform/Website for Mechanical Testing of Materials.

#### **SERVICE ACTIVITIES**

#### Journal Reviewer:

Journal of the Mechanics and Physics of Solids, Acta Materialia, Scripta Materialia, Mechanics of Materials, Geoenergy Science and Engineering, Engineering with Computers, Engineering Applications of Artificial Intelligence

# **Symposium Scribe:**

AmeriMech Symposium Series on *Machine learning in heterogeneous porous materials*, October 2021, sponsored by the National Academies of Sciences, Engineering and Medicine and the U.S. National Committee on Theoretical and Applied Mechanics.

Ongoing commitment to co-authoring a review article titled "A century of fracture mechanics: from Griffith theory to machine learning" with Prof. Huajian Gao (Nanyang Technological University, Singapore; IHPC, A\*STAR, Singapore), Prof. Markus J. Buehler (MIT), Prof. George Em Karniadakis (Brown University), Prof. Pania Newell (University of Utah), and Dr. Hari Viswanathan (Los Alamos National Laboratory).

# Commitment to Building a Machine Learning-Enabled Open-Access Platform for Mechanical Testing of Materials:

My web-based platform has been available online since 2019 (https://hint1412.github.io/XLiu.github.io/SIF/).